Guide to the Elizabeth Fink Papers, 1971-2015 RL.11343
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Elizabeth Fink papers
1971-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fink, Elizabeth M., 1945-2015
Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
RL.11343
7 Linear Feet
779 Gigabytes
Elizabeth Fink was a human rights lawyer who represented prisoners killed and injured during the 1971 Attica prison uprising. The collection consists of photographs gathered as evidence used in the subsequent lawsuits on behalf of Attica prisoners, represented by Fink, as well as some copies of trial transcripts and audiovisual recordings of news coverage, interviews, and footage.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged by format: Photographs, Audiovisual Materials, and Papers; Papers largely consist of trial transcripts, printed materials, and clippings files about Attica.
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth Fink (1945-2015) was a human rights lawyer and activist who represented prisoners killed and injured during the 1971 Attica prison uprising.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Elizabeth Fink Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2016 with a subsequent gift in 2017.
Related Materials
Additional materials documenting the Attica prison revolt can be found in the Jomo Joka Omowale Papers, also held in Rubenstein Library's Human Rights Archive.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of photographs gathered as evidence used in the subsequent lawsuits on behalf of Attica prisoners, represented by Fink, as well as some copies of trial transcripts and audiovisual recordings of news coverage, interviews, and footage of Attica Correctional Facility following the Attica uprising. There are also materials collected by Fink from the Attica Brothers Legal Defense. Content includes photographs and moving images of the prison uprising; guards and officials during the standoff; the subsequent assault and retaking of the prison ("Bloody Monday") by the Russell Oswald and the NY State Police; the aftermath of the assault, including images of the re-captured prisoners, deceased prisoners, debris from the uprising, and armed guards; morgue images and fingerprints of deceased inmates and hostages; interviews and news programs about the event; images of Attica prison facilities; and images and audiovisual of Fink's memorial service and the scattering of Fink's cremated remains. Some of the images and audiovisual materials have been digitized. Images depict graphic violence, nudity, and deceased persons. Collection acquired as part of the Archive of Human Rights (Duke University).
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services in advance to request the production of listening or viewing copies.
Prison riots -- New York; Prisoners -- United States -- Civil rights; Prisoners -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Human Rights; Inmates of institutions -- Abuse of -- North Carolina -- Durham; Attica Correctional Facility; Omowale, Jomo Joka; Attica Defense Committee; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
- Attica papers and printed materials, 1971-2012
  Scope and Contents
  Printed materials about the Attica uprising and subsequent lawsuits and coverage, as well as Black Power and other items produced by the Attica Brothers Legal Defense Fund to advocate for prison reform, justice for Attica Brothers and other inmates, and civil rights. Also includes clippings about Fink and the work of the Attica Brothers Legal Defense.
  - "The Brothers of Attica," by Richard X Clark (photocopied excerpts), 1973 (Box 1)
  - Black Community News Letter, vol. 7, 1974 (Box 1)
  - "Fighting Back! Attica Memorial Book" (published by the Attica Brothers Legal Defense), 1974 (Box 1)
  - Defense Attorneys: Attica Indictments Revised List, 1974 Sept. 5 (Box 1)
  - "Awakening of a Dragon," by Attica Brother Jomo (published by the Attica Bond to Free Jomo), 1974 Oct. 31 (Box 1)
  - "Attica 1971-1975," by Annette T. Rubinstein (published by The Charter Group for a Pledge of Conscience), 1975 Dec. (Box 1)
  - Attica Speakers Bureau pamphlet, listing available speakers; from the Attica Brothers Legal Defense / Attica Brothers Offense Defense, undated (Box 1)
  - "Attica Chronology of Events 1971-1974" (published by the Attica Brothers Legal Defense), undated (Box 1)
  - "Attica: Then and Now, Still Fighting Back" (published by the Attica Committee to Free Dacajeweiah), 1978 (Box 1)
  - Attica Prison Calendar, undated (Box 1)
    Dates removed; only images from the calendar remain. Images of Attica, guards, other prisons.
  - Newspaper photocopied clippings: aftermath and autopsies of the deceased, 1971 Sept. 15 (Box 1)
  - "Attica: The Hostages' Story," New York Times photocopied clipping, 1971 Oct. 31 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings: Attica case settlements, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings: lawsuits coverage, misc., 1990s (Box 1)
  - "Attica," in Verdict, vol. 7 no. 3, 2001 (Box 1)
  - "Attica is all of us," National Lawyers Guild Spring Fling, 2006 Apr. 7 (Box 1)
  - "Remembering Attica" manuscript draft, with edits, by E. Fink, M. Deutsch, and Dennis Cunningham, 2011 (Box 4)
  - "Remembering Attica," in the New York City News of the National Lawyers Guild, 2012 Winter (Box 1)
  - Fink's framed Frederick Douglass quote (deframed), undated (Box 1)
- Attica trial materials, 1991-1997
  This series contains a portion of the trial transcripts and Fink's plaintiff brief produced on behalf of Attica prisoners as part of their lawsuit over civil rights violations during the retaking of the prison.
  - Al-Jundi vs. Oswald, etc. trial transcript, 1991 October 15-16; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Al-Jundi vs. Rockefeller, etc. trial transcripts, 1991 Dec. 30-1992 Feb. 4; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Brosig vs. Pfiel trial transcript, 1997 Jun. 25 (Box 2)
  - Plaintiff brief for the liability appeal vs. C. Pfiel, U.S. Court of Appeals, 1997 (Box 2)
- Attica photographs, 1971-1974 and undated
  Photographs and color photocopies of prints documenting the Attica uprising, police assault, and aftermath, as well as files containing photographic evidence for some of the inmate and hostage deaths following the retaking of the prison on Sept. 13 1971. Files for hostages and deceased Attica Brothers (inmates) typically include images of the dead men following the assault, morgue photographs, and occasionally fingerprints or mugshots. There are also images of Attica's facilities collected as part of an evidence-gathering exercise in 1974. A number of the prints and smaller number of negatives were digitized by a third party.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
  - Hostages, 1971
    - Cunningham, Edward, 1971 (Box 3)
    - D'Archangelo, John, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Hardie, Elmer, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Hostages, deceased (pre-morgue), 1971 (Box 3)
    - Jones, Hubert, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Lewis, Richard, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Valone, Carl, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Monteleone, John, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Werner, Elon, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Werner, Ronald, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Whalen, Harrison "Red", 1971 (Box 4)
  - Brothers/Inmates, 1971
    - Allen, William, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Barkley, Elliott James, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Barnes, John, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Davis, Bernard Lamar, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Durham, Allen, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Fuller, Willie, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Gray, Melvin, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Johnson, Emanuel, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Lundy, Charles, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Martin, Giddell, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Melville, Samuel, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Menefee, Edward, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Mentijo, Jose, 1971; 2 folders (Box 4, Box 8)
    - Menyweather, Milton III, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Moore, Richard, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Prescott, Carlos, and Jose Mentigo, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Robinson, James, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Thomas, Harold, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Ware, Melvin, 1971 (Box 3)
    - West, Willie, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Attica Documentation/Evidence, 1971-1974
    - Uprising, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Brothers and hostages on catwalks, pre-assault, 1971 Sept. 13; 2 folders (Box 4, Box 8)
    - Occupation of prison by brothers, 1971 Sept. 9-13 (Box 4)
    - Planning the assault, 1971 Sept. 9-13 (Box 4)
    - Assault, National Guard, Bloody Monday, 1971; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Assault, 1971; 2 folders (Box 4, Box 8)
    - After retaking the prison: miscellaneous, 1971; 2 folders (Box 4, Box 8)
    - Aftermath, 1971; 3 folders (Box 4, Box 8)
    - Aftermath: D-Yard after rehousing, 1971 Sept. 13 (Box 4)
    - Aftermath: "extra torture", 1971 Sept. 13 (Box 4)
    - Aftermath: surviving hostages, 1971 Sept. 13 (Box 4)
    - Aftermath: wounded troopers, 1971 Sept. 13 (Box 4)
    - Assorted slides (unlabelled), 1970s-1980s (Box 4)
      Unsorted, unlabelled slides that appear to relate to protests, evidence, and trials of the Attica Brothers. No additional context was included so slides have simply been rehoused for preservation with no further arrangement.
    - Attica architecture, 1971-1974; 2 folders (Box 4)
      One folder contains duplicate prints.
    - Brothers on the ground in D-Yard, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Prisoners, 1971; 2 folders (Box 4, Box 8)
    - Snakeline, 1971 Sept. 13 (Box 4)
    - Deceased, 1971; 4 folders (Box 4, Box 8)
      One folder contains color photocopies of prints.
    - Investigation Photos, 1971-1974 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous negatives, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Mugshots, undated (Box 4)
    - Prison exterior: aftermath, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Maps/charts of Attica prison, 1970s (Box 4)
      Evidence-gathering materials including photocopied floorplans of the prison.
    - Uprising/Assault/Aftermath color photocopies, 1971; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Unknown miscellaneous photographs, undated; 2 folders (Box 4, Box 8)
  - Attica digitized photographs and documents, Approximately 3000 digital images (JPEG and TIFF format); 225 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0003)
- Attica audiovisual materials
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of use copies.
  Original VHS and audio-cassette labels have been retained. A number of the VHS cassettes have been digitized by a third party.
  - NBC #8, 762. Dub Date: 7/11/01 (Attica 002) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0001)
  - Vanderbilt Archive, 747. News reports 1971. Footage of Bill 1971-75. NBC 9/9/71, ABC 1/4/2000. 67 minutes. (Attica 0003A + 3B), 1971-1975 (2000?) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0002)
  - NBC #7, 761. Interviews. Outside Attica, troops ammassing, troops enter prison. Mach on Washington, Rocky campaigning, Vietnam. Dub Date: 7/9/01. (Attica 03B (a)), 00:06:57 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0003, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - Attica #8, 734. Property of Dee Dee Halleck. (Attica 03B (b)), 0:32:38 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0004, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - NBC 6, #756. Attica massacre prison footage? Attica ext... Guard funeral, Bill Kunstler press Con, Attica hearing, Attica protest Harlem, shot of bill speaking. Swearing in of Gov. Rockefeller, Rockefeller Campaign, Rocky at RNC, 1964. Dub Date: 5/29/01. (Attica 004), 0:41:07 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0005, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - Attica #11, 735. Property of Dee Dee Halleck. (Attica 006B), 0:30:36 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0006, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - ABC News / Discovery, #750. Prison Riot-Five Deadly Days. TV Documentary. (Attica 007), 0:48:30 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0007, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - Vanderbilt, 745. CBS. Evening News, Walter Cronkite, Bill tries to enter. Day of raid, Oswald orig. press con, Bobby Seal. (Attica 008 (a)), 1971 Sept. 13; 0:08:06 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0008, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - NBC 4, 752. Attica massacre, Bill Int. outside, Bobby Seal int., Kent State, LA Riots, Panthers, Vietnam, Chicago, Tom Harden, Lots of random stuff. Dub Date: 4/23/02. (Attica 008 (b)), 0:36:00 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0009, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - NBC 1, 740. Attica Hearings. Tape 1. Dub Date: 1/19/01. (Attica 009A + B) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0010)
  - NBC 3, 742. Attica aftermath, vigil outside of guards families. Guard funeral. Observers Arthur Eve interviews with guards, Oswald press con. Harlem funeral. Prisoner funerals. Dub Date: 2/13/01. (Attica 010), 1971 Sept. 17 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0011)
  - NBC 2, 741. Tape 2. Dub Date: 1/21/01. (Attica 011) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0012)
  - National Action Network. Rev. Al Sharpton / Kunstler / Crew Family. Sharon Carter / CUNY. (Attica 012), 1999 June 5 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0013)
  - Brosig / Makowski. Frank BB Smith (?) 7/25/92. Alan Makowski 7/25/94. David Brosig 7/27/92. (Attica 013) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0014)
  - Attica State Prison Uprising - Sept. 1971, 16:10. Anthony Strollo, Four Long Days - Return to Attica, WKBW-TV, TZA-TV. (Attica 014), 0:48:09 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0015, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - ABC, #758. Lumiere. TR #14375 / OR #23602. (Attica 017), 2001 June 13 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0016)
  - Robert Marvin. Clyde Pope. (Attica 018), 1994 Aug. 12 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0017)
  - Visual Studies Workshop #88. Arthur Eve Speech Reel 1. (Attica 019) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0018)
  - NewsSource 13. Attica Settlement, #746. Court. (Attica 020) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0019)
  - Attica 2. Attica Memorial Ride. From Tony Strollo. (Attica 026), 2000 Sept. 9 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0020)
  - Healthcare Colloquium. Keynote Roundtable. (Attica 027) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0021)
  - Healthcare Colloquium. Keynote Con't. ADA Panel. RUST Panel. (Attica 028) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0022)
  - Attica Damages Award (Attica 029), 2000 Aug. 28 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0023)
  - Attica Panel. Liman Professorship. Inaugural Events. (Attica 030), 1998 Nov. 5 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0024)
  - Showtime. Attica: The Aftermath. Added value show. Writer Producer: Beth Kieran. (Attica 031) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0025)
  - Court TV. Johnnie Cochran Tonight (Attica 032), 1999 Sept. 13 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0026)
  - Bill Kunstler Memorial (Attica 033) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0027)
  - Untitled (Attica 034). Red Circle Sticker. (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0028)
  - #701, IST Duplicate of Dubbing Last 2 Min #2 and 3A. Vidipax, Reel #13. (Attica 037), 1972 Mar. 11 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0029)
  - #702, Attica video copy - slected parts of original video tapes 1,2,3 & 4. Vidipax, Reel #9. (Attica 038), 0:19:59 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0030, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - #704, ... (4). Vidipax, reel #12. (Attica 039) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0031)
  - #705. DUD #1 from MYSA. Vidipax, Reel #11. (Attica 040) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0032)
  - #706, Tape #1 Attica Riot, Original. Vidipax, Reel #10. (Attica 041), 1971 Sept. 9-10; 0:19:57 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0033, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - #707, Inside Blocks other than D-Yard. Vidipax, Reel #8. (Attica 042), 1971 Sept. 13; 0:22:37 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0034, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - #708, Tape #2, 9,10,11 - 71. Troops, other blocks (i.e. building barricades). Vidipax, Reel #7. (Attica 043) (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0035)
  - #709, Dubbing of #1. EIAJ. No Eliminations, no editing. Shots inside yard, no sound, some slow motion, some good shots, some very poor. Vidipax, Reel #6. (Attica 044), 1971 Mar. 13; 0:18:37 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0036, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - #710, Dubbing of 2. EIAJ. No eliminations, no editing. Poor quality, some tracking issues, hostages on catwalk, some good shots, some really poor. Vidipax, Reel #4. (Attica 045), 1972 Mar. 13; 0:30:39 (Box 5, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0037, Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0005)
  - 711 (11). Vidipax, Reel #23. (Attica 046) (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0038)
  - #712 (12), Court of Clams. Vidipax, Reel #22. (Attica 047), 1978 Oct. 16 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0039)
  - #713, IST Duplicate of Dubbing of 3B EIAJ... Poor quality but original footage. Vidipax, Reel #14. (Attica 048), 1972 Mar. 12 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0040)
  - #717, State Police. Includes assault footage. Vidipax, Reel #24. (Attica 049) (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0041)
  - #720, Attica Consolidation Tape (1 of 2). Tape #3. Vidipax, Reel #17. (Attica 050) (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0042)
  - #721, Attica tape. Vidipax, Reel #18. (Attica 051), 1971 Sept. 13 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0043)
  - #724, Hostage Sem. N.Y.S. Comm. Of Corrections. Vidipax, Reel #19. (Attica 052) (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0044)
  - Various Shots. Vidipax, Reel #15. (Attica 053), 1971 Sept. 11-13 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0045)
  - Attica Bar Assoc. Vidipax, Reel #25. (Attica 054) (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0046)
  - Goerge Mitchell, 9/27/97. Gary Haynes, 7/26/97. Goerge Shorts. Daniel Sheppard., 1997 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0047)
  - Ezell Vance, 1997 Jul. 27 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0048)
  - ABC, #753. Lumiere, 22975, T#14375e. Commission., 2001 Apr. 23 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0049)
  - ABC. Lumiere, 23880. T #14375F., 2001 Jul. 11 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0050)
  - ABC, #744. Lumiere, 22676. T #14375. Partly Attica., 2001 Apr. 4 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0051)
  - Lumiere Productions, Attica. Liz Fink. #71., 2001 Oct. 26 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0052)
  - Lumiere Productions, Attica. Liz Fink. #70., 2001 Oct. 26 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0053)
  - Lumiere Productions, Attica. Liz Fink. #69., 2001 Oct. 26 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0054)
  - Courtroom and outside Courtroom footage of Day Doaruba Moore was released. (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0055)
  - ABC Screener #4, #757. Lumiere, T #14375., 1971 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0056)
  - Ghosts of Attica, 64. 89:20 mins. First Run Icarus Films. Color case., 2001 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0057)
  - Ghosts of Attica. 90 mins. First Run Icarus Films. Transparent case., 2001 (Box 6, Video-cassette RL11343-VHS-0058)
  - 712. Court of Clams. Claimant's ex: 56. EIA-J. Vidipax, Reel #22. (Attica 035), 1978 Oct. 16 (Box 6, Video-reel RL11343-Vid1-0001)
  - 713. IST Duplicate of Dubbing of 3B. EIAJ. After assault. Vidipax, Reel #14. (Attica 036), 1972 Mar. 12 (Box 6, Video-reel RL11343-Vid1-0002)
  - WDNY. Case #75-CV-132. Judicial officer: John T. Elfvin., 1993 Jan. 19 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL11343-CS-0001)
  - Untitled (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL11343-CS-0002)
  - Summation, 3A, 3B. Liz. (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL11343-CS-0003)
  - The Struggle Within. 30 Years after the Attica Rebellion. Freedom Archives. 29 minutes. (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL11343-CS-0004)
  - "Where We Live" (WBAI). w/ Zenzile Khoisan, Sally O'Brien. Attica., 1991 Jul. 9 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL11343-CS-0005)
  - Illegible (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL11343-CS-0006)
  - Attica digitized audiovisual materials, Approximately 40 video files (QuickTime format); 450 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0002)
  - Attica born-digital audiovisual materials, 5 video files (Quicktime and MP4 formats); approximately 70 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0001)
- Post-Attica photographs and audiovisual materials
  - Other legal advocacy digital audiovisual materials, 3 video files (MPEG-4 format); approximately 0.04 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0004)
  - Memorial digital photographs and audiovisual materials, 2015; Digital images (JPEG and Camera Raw formats) and video files (Quicktime and MPEG-4 format); approxiamtely 29 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11343-SET-0004)